In the ocean,
في المحيط
what is the common point
ما النقطة المشركة
between oil, plastic and radioactivity?
بين النفط والبلاستيك والنشاط الإشعاعي؟
On the top line, this is the BP oil spill:
في السطر العلوي، هذه بقعة نفط بريتيش بتروليوم:
billions of barrels of oil gushing
مليارات البراميل من النفط تدفقت
in the Gulf of Mexico.
في خليج المكسيك.
The middle line is millions of tons of
أما السطر الأوسط فهي ملايين الأطنان من
plastic debris accumulating in our ocean,
الأنقاض البلاستيكية تتراكم في المحيط،
and the third line is radioactive material
والسطر الثالث هو المواد الإشعاعية
leaking from Fukushima nuclear power plant
وهي تتسرب من محطة فوكوشيما للطاقة النووية
in the Pacific Ocean.
في المحيط الهادئ.
Well, the three big problems have in common
حسنا، المشاكل الثلاثة لديها قاسم مشترك
that they are man-made problems
هو أنها مشاكل سببها الإنسان
but they are controlled by natural forces.
لكن يتم التحكم فيها من طرف قوى طبيعية.
This should make us feel very, terribly awful
يجب أن يجعلنا هذا نحس بشناعة فظيعة
as much as it should make us feel hopeful,
بقدر ما يجب أن يجعلنا نشعر بالأمل،
because if we have the power to create these problems,
لأنه إن كانت لدينا القدرة على خلق هذه المشاكل،
we may as well have the power
قد تكون لدينا القدرة كذلك
to remediate these problems.
على علاج هذه المشاكل.
But what about natural forces?
لكن ماذا عن القوى الطبيعية؟
Well, that's exactly what I want to talk about today,
حسنا، ذلك بالضبط ما أرغب في الحديث بخصوصه اليوم،
is how we can use these natural forces
هو كيف يمكن استخدام القوى الطبيعية
to remediate these man-made problems.
لعلاج هذه المشاكل التي سببها الإنسان.
When the BP oil spill happened,
حين حدث تسرب نفط بريتيش بتروليوم،
I was working at MIT, and I was in charge
كنت أعمل في إم آي تي، وقد كنت مسؤولا
of developing an oil spill-cleaning technology.
عن تطوير تقنية لتنظيف بقعة النفط.
And I had a chance to go in the Gulf of Mexico
وقد أتيحت لي الفرصة للذهاب إلى خليج المكسيك
and meet some fishermen and see
ومقابلة بعض الصيادين ورؤية
the terrible conditions in which they were working.
الظروف الفظيعة التي كانوا يعملون فيها.
More than 700 of these boats,
أكثر من 700 من هذه القوارب،
which are fishermen boats repurposed
والتي هي قوارب صيادين تم تعديلها
with oil absorbent in white
بإضافة ممتصات للنفط بيضاء
and oil containment in orange, were used,
وحاويات للنفط بالبرتقالي، تم استخدامها،
but they only collected three percent of the oil on the surface,
لكنها جمعت 3 في المئة فقط من النفط على السطح،
and the health of the cleaners
وصحة المنظفين
were very deeply affected.
تأثرت بشكل كبير.
I was working on a very interesting technology
لقد كنت أشتغل على تقنية مثيرة للغاية
at MIT, but it was a very long-term view
في إم آي تي، لكنها كانت رؤية بعيدة المدى
of how to develop technology,
لكيف يمكن تطوير التقنية،
and it was going to be a very expensive technology,
وقد كانت ستكون تقنية بالغة التكلفة،
and also it would be patented.
وسيتم كذلك تسجيل براءة اختراعها.
So I wanted to develop something that we could
وبالتالي أردت تطوير شيء يمكننا
develop very fast, that would be cheap,
تطويره بسرعة كبيرة، وأن يكون رخيصا،
and that would be open-source, so, because
وأن يكون مفتوح المصدر، لذا، ولأن
oil spills are not only happening in the Gulf of Mexico,
بقع النفط لم تكن تحدث في خليج المكسيك فقط،
and that would be using renewable energy.
وأنها ستستخدم الطاقة المتجددة.
So I quit my dream job,
وبالتالي تركت مهنة أحلامي،
and I moved to New Orleans,
وانتقلت إلى نيو أورلينز،
and I kept on studying how the oil spill was happening.
واستمريت في دراسة كيفية حدوث بقع النفط.
Currently, what they were doing is
حاليا، ما كانوا يقومون به هو
that they were using these small fishing boats,
أنهم كانوا يستخدمون قوارب الصيد الصغيرة هذه،
and they were cleaning clean lines in an ocean of dirt.
وكانوا ينظفون خطوطا نقية في محيط من القذارة.
If you're using the exact same amount of surface
إن كنت تستخدم نفس مقدار المساحة
of oil absorbent, but you're just paying attention
من ممتصات النفط، لكن تهتم فقط
to natural patterns, and if you're going up the winds,
بالأنماط الطبيعية، وإن كنت تذهب في عكس اتجاه الريح،
you can collect a lot more material.
يمكنك جمع الكثير من المواد.
If you're multiplying the rig,
إن كنت تضاعف مساحة التماس،
so you multiply how many layers of absorbent
وبالتالي تضاعف عدد طبقات الامتصاص
you're using, you can collect a lot more.
التي تستخدمها، مما يمكنك من جمع قدر أكبر.
But it's extremely difficult to move oil absorbent
لكن من الصعب جدا تحريك ممتص النفط
against the winds, the surface currents and the waves.
عكس الرياح وتيارات السطح والأمواج.
These are enormous forces.
هذه قوى هائلة.
So the very simple idea was to use the ancient technique
وبالتالي الفكرة البسيطة جدا كانت في استخدام تقنية
of sailing and tacking of the wind
الإبحار العتيقة وتغيير الاتجاه ريحيا
to capture or intercept the oil
لالتقاط أو اعتراض النفط
that is drifting down the wind.
الذي ينجرف في اتجاه الريح.
So this didn't require any invention.
وبالتالي فهذا لم يستدعي أي اختراع.
We just took a simple sailing boat
قمنا فقط بأخذ قارب إبحار بسيط
and we tried to pull something long and heavy,
وحاولنا جر شيء طويل وثقيل،
but as we tacked back and forth,
لكن ونحن نغير الاتجاه ذهابا وإيابا،
what we lost was two things:
ما فقدناه كان أمرين:
we were losing pulling power and direction.
كنا نفقد قوة الجذب والتوجيه.
And so, I thought, what about if we just take the rudder
وبالتالي، فكرت في ماذا لو قمنا فقط بأخذ الدفة
from the back of the boat to the front,
من خلف القارب إلى المقدمة،
would we have better control?
هل سنحصل على تحكم أحسن؟
So I built this small sailing robot
وبالتالي بنيت آلي الإبحار الصغير هذا
with the rudder at the front,
بالدفة في المقدمة،
and I was trying to pull something very long and heavy,
وقد كنت أحاول جر شيء طويل جدا وثقيل،
so that's a four-meter-long object just to pull,
وبالتالي فذلك جسم بطول أربعة أمتار لجره فقط،
and I was surprised with just a 14-centimeter rudder,
وقد تفاجأت أنه بدفة من طول 14 سنتيمترا فقط،
I could control four meters of absorbent.
استطعت التحكم في أربعة أمتار من الممتص.
Then I was so happy that I kept playing with the robot,
ثم كنت فرحا جدا لدرجة أنني استمريت في اللعب بالآلي،
and so you see the robot has
وبالتالي ترون أن الآلي لديه
a front rudder here.
دفة أمامية هنا.
Normally it's at the back.
هي عادة في الخلف.
And, playing, I realized that the maneuverability
و، أثناء اللعب، أدركت أن القدرة التناورية
of this was really amazing,
له كانت مذهلة للغاية،
and I could avoid an obstacle at the very last second,
وكنت أستطيع تفادي عائق في آخر لحظة،
more maneuverable than a normal boat.
له قدرة تناورية أكثر من القارب العادي.
Then I started publishing online, and
ثم بدأت بالنشر على الإنترنت،
some friends from Korea, they started being
وبعض الأصدقاء من كوريا، بدؤوا في
interested in this, and we made a boat
الإهتمام بهذا، فصنعنا قاربا
which has a front rudder and a back rudder,
بدفة أمامية ودفة خلفية،
so we started interacting with this,
وبالتالي بدأنا في التفاعل مع هذا،
and it was slightly better,
وقد كان أحسن بقليل،
although it was very small and a bit off balance,
على الرغم من أنه كان صغيرا جدا وغير متوازن قليلا،
but then we thought,
لكننا فكرنا بعد ذلك،
what if we have more than two points of control?
ماذا لو كان لدينا أكثر من نقطتي تحكم؟
What if the entire boat becomes a point of control?
ماذا لو صار كل القارب نقطة تحكم؟
What if the entire boat changes shape?
ماذا لو أمكن القارب بأكمله أن يغير شكله؟
So — (Applause)
وبالتالي -- (تصفيق)
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم. (تصفيق)
And so that's the beginning of Protei,
وبالتالي كانت تلك بداية Protei،
and that's the first boat in history
وذلك كان أول قارب في التاريخ
that completely changed the shape of the hull
يغير شكل هيكله بشكل كامل
in order to control it,
من أجل التحكم فيه،
and the properties of sailing that we get
وخصائص الإبحار التي نحصل عليها
are very superior compared to a normal boat.
هي متفوقة جدا مقارنة بالقارب العادي.
When we're turning, we have the feeling of surfing,
حين كنا ندور، كان لدينا إحساس يشبه ركوب الأمواج،
and the way it's going up-wind, it's very efficient.
والطريقة التي يمشي بها في اتجاه الرياح كانت فعالة للغاية.
This is low speed, low wind speed,
هذه سرعة بطيئة، سرعة ريح بطيئة،
and the maneuverability is very increased,
والقدرة التناورية تتزايد جدا،
and here I'm going to do a small jibe,
وهنا سأؤدي انعطافا صغيرا،
and look at the position of the sail.
وأنظر في وضع الشراع.
What's happening is that, because the boat changes shape,
ما يحدث هو أنه، بسبب أن القارب يغير شكله،
the position of the front sail and the main sail
وضع الشراع الأمامي والشراع الرئيسي
are different to the wind.
هو في اتجاهين مختلفين بالنسبة للريح.
We're catching wind from both sides.
وبذلك نلتقط الريح من كلا الاتجاهين.
And this is exactly what we're looking [for]
وهذا بالضبط ما نبحث [عنه]
if we want to pull something long and heavy.
إن أردنا جر شيء طويل وثقيل.
We don't want to lose pulling power, nor direction.
لا نريد أن نفقد قوة الجر أو الاتجاه.
So, I wanted to know if this was possible
وهكذا، أردت أن أعرف إن كان ممكنا
to put this at an industrial level,
أن أرتقي بهذا إلى مستوى صناعي،
so we made a large boat with a large sail,
وبالتالي صنعنا قاربا كبيرا بشراع كبير،
and with a very light hull, inflatable,
وبهيكل خفيف جدا وقابل للنفخ،
very small footprint,
وأثر صغير جدا،
so we have a very big size and power ratio.
وبالتالي لدينا حجم كبير جدا ونسبة قوة أكبر.
After this, we wanted to see if we could
بعد هذا، أردنا رؤية إن أمكننا
implement this and automate the system,
تطبيق هذا وجعل النظام آليا،
so we used the same system but we added
وبالتالي استخدمنا نفس النظام لكننا أضفنا
a structure to it so we could activate the machine.
بنية إليه بحيث يمكن تفعيل الآلة.
So, we used the same bladder-inflated system,
وبالتالي، استخدمنا نفس نظام المثانة المتضخمة،
and we took it for testing.
وأخذناه لنجربه.
So this is happening in the Netherlands.
إذ حدث هذا في هولندا.
We tried in the water without any skin or ballast
جربناه في الماء من دون أي غطاء أو أوزان
just to see how it works.
فقط لرؤية كيف يعمل.
And then we mounted a camera for controlling it,
ثم ركبنا آلة تصوير للتحكم فيه،
but quickly we saw that we would need
لكننا رأينا بسرعة أننا قد نحتاج
a lot more weight at the bottom,
إلى الكثير من الثقل في الأسفل،
so we had to take it back to the lab,
وبالتالي كان علينا إرجاعه إلى المختبر،
and then we built a skin around it,
ثم بنينا غطاء حوله،
we put batteries, remote controllers, and then
وضعنا بطاريات وأجهزة تحكم عن بعد، ثم
we put it in the water and then we
وضعناه في الماء ثم
let it go in the water and see how well it would work,
تركناه يذهب إلى الماء لرؤية إلى أي مدى سيشتغل،
so let some rope out, and hope it's going to work,
لذلك أفلتنا الحبل على أمل أن يعمل،
and it worked okay, but we still have a long way.
وقد اشتغل بشكل جيد، لكن لا يزال لدينا طريق طويل.
Our small prototype has given us good insight
نموذجنا الأولي الصغير أعطانا تبصرا جيدا
that it's working very well,
أنه يعمل بشكل جيد،
but we still need to work a lot more on this.
لكن لا نزال في حاجة إلى العمل أكثر عليه.
So what we are doing is an accelerated evolution
وبالتالي ما نقوم به هو تطور مسرّع
of sailing technology.
لتقنية الإبحار.
We went from a back rudder to a front rudder
انتقلنا من الدفة الخلفية إلى الدفة الأمامية
to two rudders to multiple rudders
إلى دفتين ودفات متعددة
to the whole boat changing shape,
إلى جعل كامل القارب يغير شكله،
and the more we are moving forward,
وبقدر ما نتقدم نحو الأمام،
and the more the design looks simple and cute. (Laughter)
بقدر ما يبدو التصميم بسيطا ولطيفا (ضحك)
But I wanted to show you a fish because --
لكن أردت أن أعرض عليكم سمكة لأنه --
In fact, it's very different from a fish.
في الواقع، هذا مختلف جدا عن السمك.
A fish will move because -- by changing like this,
تتحرك السمكة بسبب -- بالتغير هكذا،
but our boat is propelled by the wind still,
لكن قاربنا مدفوع بالريح بثبات
and the hull controls the trajectory.
فيتحكم الهيكل في المسار.
So I brought to you for the first time on the TED stage
وبالتالي أحضرت لكم ولأول مرة على خشبة TED
Protei Number Eight. It's not the last one,
Protei الثامن. ليس بالنموذج النهائي،
but it's a good one for making demos.
لكنه جيد لعرض الفكرة
So the first thing as I show you in the video is
وبالتالي أول شيء كما أريتكم في الفيديو هو
that we may be able to control the trajectory
أننا قد نستطيع التحكم في مسار
of a sailing boat better,
قارب إبحار بشكل أحسن،
or we may be able to never be in irons,
أو قد نستطيع ألا نكون أبدا عكس اتجاه الريح،
so never facing the wind,
وهكذا لن نكون أبدا في مواجهة الريح،
we always can catch the wind from both sides.
نستطيع دائما التقاط الريح من كلا الجهتين.
But new properties of a sailing boat.
إنها خصائص جديدة لقارب إبحار.
So if you're looking at the boat from this side,
وبالتالي إن كنتم تنظرون إلى القارب من هذه الجهة،
this might remind you of an airplane profile.
قد يذكركم هذا بمظهر طائرة.
An airplane, when you're moving in this direction,
حين تتحرك في هذا الاتجاه فإن الطائرة
starts to lift, and that's how it takes off.
تبدأ في الارتفاع وبذلك تقلع.
Now, if you're taking the same system,
الآن، إن أخذت نفس النظام،
and you're putting vertical, you're bending,
ووضعته عموديا وقمت بتقويسه
and if you're moving this way forward,
وإن كنت تتجه في هذا الطريق نحو الأمام،
your instinct will tell you that you might go this way,
سيخبرك حدسك أنك قد تذهب في هذا الاتجاه،
but if you're moving fast enough,
لكن إن كنت تسرع بما فيه الكفاية،
you might create what we call lateral lift,
قد تخلق ما نسميه الارتفاع الجانبي،
so we could get further or closer to the wind.
وبالتالي نستطيع أن نذهب أبعد أو أقرب من الرياح.
Other property is this:
خاصية أخرى هي:
A normal sailing boat has a centerboard here
قارب إبحار عادي برافد مركزي هنا
and a rudder at the back,
ودفة في الخلف،
and these two things are what creates most
وهذان الأمران هي ما يخلق جلّ
resistance and turbulence behind the boat,
المقاومة والاضطراب خلف القارب،
but because this doesn't have either
لكن لأن هذا القارب لا يتوفر لا على
a centerboard or a rudder,
رافدة مركزية ولا دفة،
we hope that if we keep working on this hull design
نأمل أنه إن واصلنا العمل على تصميم هذا الهيكل
we can improve and have less resistance.
يمكن أن نحسن ونتوفر على مقاومة أقل.
The other thing is, most boats, when they reach
الأمر الآخر هو، معظم القوارب، حين تصل
a certain speed, and they are going on waves,
سرعة معينة، وتمشي على الأمواج،
they start to hit and slap on the surface of the water,
تبدأ في ضرب وصفع سطح الماء،
and a lot of the energy moving forward is lost.
والكثير من الطاقة تضيع وهو يتقدم للأمام.
But if we're going with the flow,
لكن إن كنا نمشي وفقا للتيار،
if we pay attention to natural patterns
إن انتبهنا للأنماط الطبيعية
instead of trying to be strong,
بدل محاولة التقوية،
but if you're going with the flow, we may absorb
لكن إن كنا نمشي وفقا للتيار قد نمتص
a lot of environmental noises, so the wave energy,
الكثير من الضجيج البيئي، وبالتالي الطاقة الموجية،
to actually save some energy to move forward.
للمحافظة على الطاقة أثناء المشي نحو الأمام.
So we may have developed the technology
وبالتالي قد نكون قد طوّرنا التقنية
which is very efficient for pulling something long and heavy,
التي هي فعالة لجر شيء طويل وثقيل،
but the idea is, what is the purpose of technology
لكن الفكرة هي، ما الهدف من التقنية
if it doesn't reach the right hands?
إن لم تصل إلى الأيادي الصحيحة؟
Normal technology or innovation happens like this:
التقانة العادية أو الابتكار يحدث كما يلي:
Somebody has an interesting idea,
أحدهم لديه فكرة مثيرة،
some other scientist or engineer,
عالم أو مهندس آخر،
they take it to the next level, they make a theory about it
يأخذون الفكرة إلى المستوى التالي، يشكلون حولها نظرية
and maybe they patent it,
وربما يسجلون براءة اختراعها،
and then some industry will make a contract
ثم تأتي إحدى الشركات لكتابة عقد
of exclusivity to manufacture and sell it,
أو تتفرد بتصنيعها وبيعها،
and then, eventually, a buyer will buy it,
ثم وأخيرا، يشتريها مشتر،
and we hope that they are going to use [it] for a good purpose.
ونأمل أنهم سيستخدمونه في الخير.
What we really want is that this innovation happens
ما نريده حقا هو أن يحصل هذا الابتكار
continuously. The inventor and engineers
باستمرار. المخترع والمهندسون
and also the manufacturers and everybody
والمصنعون والجميع
works at the same time, but this would be sterile
يعملون في نفس الوقت، لكن هذا سيكون عقيما
if this was happening in a parallel and uncrossed process.
إن كان هذا يحصل في عملية موازية وغير متقاطعة.
What you really want is not a sequential,
ما نريده حقا ليس هو تطور تسلسلي
not parallel development.
ولا متوازي.
You want to have a network of innovation.
نريد التوفر على شبكة للابتكار.
You want everybody, like we're doing now,
نريد الجميع كما نفعل الآن،
to work at the same time, and that can only happen
أن يعمل في نفس الوقت، وهذا يمكن فقط أن يحصل
if these people all together decide to share the information,
إن قرر كل هؤلاء الناس مشاركة المعلومات،
and that's exactly what open hardware is about.
وذلك بالضبط الغرض من العتاد المفتوح.
It's to replace competition by collaboration.
هو تعويض المنافسة بالتعاون.
It's to transform any new product into a new market.
هو تحويل أي منتج جديد إلى سوق جديدة.
So what is open hardware?
إذن ما هو العتاد المفتوح؟
Essentially, open hardware is a license.
أساسا، العتاد المفتوح هو رخصة.
It's just an intellectual property setup.
هي فقط تثبيت لخاصية فكرية.
It means that everybody is free to use,
تعني أن الكل حر في الاستخدام
modify and distribute, and in exchange
والتعديل والتوزيع والتبادل
we only ask for two things:
نطلب فقط أمرين:
The name is credited -- the name of the project --
أن يتم نسب العمل لأصحابه -- اسم المشروع --
and also the people who make improvement,
والناس كذلك الذين يقومون بالتحسين،
they share back with the community.
يشاركون ذلك مع المجتمع.
So it's a very simple condition.
وبالتالي هو شرط بسيط جدا.
And I started this project alone in a garage in New Orleans,
وقد بدأت هذا المشروع وحيدا في مرأب في نيو أورلينز،
but quickly after I wanted to publish and share
لكن بعد ذلك بوقت وجيز أردت أن أنشر وأشارك
this information, so I made a Kickstarter,
هذه المعلومات، وبالتالي أنشأت حسابا في موقع Kickstarter،
which is a crowd-fundraising platform,
والذي هو منصة حشودية لجمع التبرعات،
and in about one month we fundraised 30,000 dollars.
وبعد حوالي الشهر جمعنا 30,000 دولار.
With this money, I hired a team of young engineers
وبهذا المال، وظفت فريقا من المهندسين الشباب
from all over the world, and we rented a factory
من جميع أنحاء العالم، واستأجرنا مصنعا
in Rotterdam in the Netherlands.
في روتردام في هولندا.
We were peer-learning, we were engineering,
كنا نتعلم من بعضنا البعض ونهندس،
we were making things, prototyping,
وكنا نصنع أشياء وننمذجها
but most importantly we were trying our prototypes
لكن، وبشكل أهم، كنا نجرب النماذج الأولية
in the water as often as possible,
في الماء بقدر الإمكان،
to fail as quickly as possible, to learn from.
لنفشل في أقرب وقت ممكن، لنتعلم من ذلك.
This is a proud member of Protei from Korea,
هذا عضو فخور في Protei من كوريا،
and on the right side, this is a multiple-masts
وعلى اليمين هنا، هذا تصميم متعدد الصواري
design proposed by a team in Mexico.
مقترح من طرف فريق في المكسيك.
This idea really appealed to Gabriella Levine
وقد أسرت الفكرة غابرييلا ليفين
in New York, and so she decided to prototype
في نيويورك، وبالتالي قررت أن تصنع نموذجا أوليا
this idea that she saw, and she documented
للفكرة التي رأتها، ووثقت
every step of the process,
كل خطوة من العملية،
and she published it on Instructables,
ونشرتها على موقع Instructables،
which is a website for sharing inventions.
والذي هو موقع لمشاركة الاختراعات.
Less than one week after,
بعد أقل من أسبوع،
this is a team in Eindhoven, it's a school of engineering.
هذا فريق من ايندهوفن، إنها مدرسة هندسة.
They made it, but they eventually published
قاموا بصناعته، لكنهم قاموا في النهاية بنشر
a simplified design.
تصميم مبسط.
They also made it into an Instructable,
وقد وضعوه كذلك على موقع Instructable،
and in less than one week, they had
وفي أقل من أسبوع، حصلوا على
almost 10,000 views, and they got many new friends.
ما يقارب 10,000 مشاهدة وكونوا صداقات جديدة.
We're working on also simpler technology,
نحن نعمل كذلك على تقنية أبسط،
not that complex, with younger people
ليست بذلك التعقيد، مع أشخاص يافعين
and also older people,
وكذلك مع من هم أكبر،
like this dinosaur is from Mexico. (Laughter)
مثل هذا الديناصور من المكسيك. (ضحك)
So Protei is now an international network
وبالتالي فProtei هي الآن شبكة دولية
of innovation for selling technology
من الابتكار لبيع التقنية
using this shape-shifting hull.
باستخدام هذا الهيكل المتحول الشكل.
And what puts us together is that we have a common,
والذي يجمعنا هو أنه لدينا،
at least, global understanding
على الأقل فهم موحد وعالمي
of what the word "business" is, or what it should be.
لما تعنيه كلمة "أعمال"، أو ما يجب أن تكون عليه.
This is how most work today.
هكذا يشتغل الأغلبية اليوم.
Business as usual is saying, what's most important
الأعمال كما المعتاد هي مقولة، الأكثر أهمية
is to make lots of profit, and you'll be using
هو أن تحقق أرباحا، وستستخدم
technology for that, and people will be your work force,
التقنية من أجل ذلك، والناس سيكونون قوتك العالملة
instrumentalized,
وأدواتك
and environment is usually the last priority.
والبيئة في العادة في آخر الأولويات.
It will be just a way to, say, greenwash your audience
ستكون فقط طريقة للتبييض البيئي لجمهوركم على سبيل المثال،
and, say, increase your price tag.
وزيادة بطاقة أسعارك.
What we're trying to do, or what we believe,
ما نحاول القيام به، أو ما نؤمن به،
because this is how we believe the world really works,
لأننا نعتقد أن العالم يعمل هكذا،
is that without the environment you have nothing.
هو أنه من دون البيئية ليس لدينا شيء.
We have the people so we need to protect each other, yes,
نعم، لدينا الناس وبالتالي نحتاج لحماية بعضنا البعض،
and we're a technology company,
ونحن شركة تقنية،
and profit is necessary to make this happen. (Applause)
والأرباح أساسية لتحقيق ذلك. (تصفيق)
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم. (تصفيق)
If we have the courage to understand or accept
إن كانت لدينا الشجاعة لفهم أو قبول
that this actually how the world really works,
أن هذه في الواقع كيفية اشتغال العالم،
and this is the order of priority that we need to choose,
وهذا هو ترتيب الأولويات الذي يجب أن نختاره،
then it makes obvious why we need
وبالتالي يجعل من الواضح سبب حاجتنا
to choose open hardware for developing environmental
لاختيار العتاد المفتوح لتطوير التقنية البيئية،
technology, because we need to share information.
لأننا نحتاج إلى مشاركة المعلومات.
What's next for us?
ما التالي بالنسبة لنا؟
So, this small machine that you've seen,
حسنا، هذه الآلة الصغيرة التي قد رأيتموها،
we're hoping to make small toys like
نأمل أن نصنع ألعاب Protei صغيرة
one-meter remote control Protei that you can upgrade --
بطول متر واحد بتحكم عن بعد يمكن ترقيتها --
so replace the remote control parts by Androids,
وبالتالي تعويض أجزاء التحكم عن بعد بأندرويد،
so the mobile phone, and Arduino micro-controller,
والهاتف المحمول والمتحكم الدقيق أردوينو،
so you could be controlling this
وبالتالي يمكنك التحكم في هذا
from your mobile phone, your tablet.
من هاتفك المحمول أو جهازك اللوحي.
Then what we want to do is create six-meter versions
ثم ما نريد القيام به هو إنشاء نسخة بطول ستة أمتار
so we can test the maximum performance of these machines,
حتى نقوم بتجربة أقصى أداء لهذه الآلات،
so we can go at very, very high speed.
حتى نستطيع التحرك في سرعات كبيرة للغاية.
So imagine yourself.
لذا تخيلوا بأنفسكم.
You are laying down in a flexible torpedo,
أنكم متكئون على طوربيد مرن،
sailing at high speed,
تبحرون بسرعة كبيرة،
controlling the shape of the hull with your legs
متحكمين في شكل الهيكل بأرجلكم
and controlling the sail with your arms.
ومتحكمين في الشراع بأذرعكم.
So that's what we're looking for developing. (Applause)
وبالتالي هذا ما نسعى لتطويره. (تصفيق)
And we replace the human being --
ونعوض الإنسان --
to go, for example, for measuring radioactivity,
للذهاب وقياس مستوى الإشعاع،
you don't want a human to be sailing those robots --
لا تريد من إنسان أن يبحر بتلك القوارب --
with batteries, motors, micro-controllers and sensors.
ببطاريات ومحركات ومتحكمات دقيقة وأجهزة استشعار.
This is what our teammates, we dream of at night.
هذا ما يحلم به زملائي في الفريق ليلا.
We hope that we can sometime clean up oil spills,
نأمل أننا سنستطيع في وقت ما تنظيف بقع النفط،
or we can gather or collect plastic in the ocean,
أو نجمع ونلتقط البلاستيك من المحيط،
or we can have swarms of our machines
أو نتوفر على أسراب من أجهزتنا
controlled by multi-player video game engines
متحكم فيها بمحركات ألعاب فيديو متعددة اللاعبين
to control many of these machines,
للتحكم في العديد من هذه الآلات،
to monitor coral reefs
لمراقبة الشعاب المرجانية
or to monitor fisheries.
أو مراقبة مصايد الأسماك.
Our hope is that we can use open hardware technology
أملنا أن نستخدم تقنية العتاد المفتوح
to better understand and protect our oceans.
لنفهم ونحمي محيطاتنا بشكل أحسن.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)